<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Observations on Saman Barghi</title>
    <link>http://samanbarghi.com/categories/observations/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Observations on Saman Barghi</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://samanbarghi.com/categories/observations/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Some Notes on Facebook Hacker Cup Qualification Round</title>
      <link>http://samanbarghi.com/2011/01/11/some-notes-on-facebook-hacker-cup-qualification-round</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://samanbarghi.com/2011/01/11/some-notes-on-facebook-hacker-cup-qualification-round</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Monday, January 10 was the last day to submit your answers to get qualified for Facebook Hacker Cup. It started from January 7, and lasted for 3 days. There were three problems presented on the competition website, to be solved by participants. Problems were provided with sample input and output, and there were no time limits to browse through the problems and to develop your code. To answer each problem, competitors had to download an input and submit their output, yet they only had 6 minutes, after they downloaded the input, to submit their answers through the form provided. There were absolutely no limitations on choosing the programming language (I used Perl), nor on the way you code your solution, cause there were no need to upload your source code. All three problems were fairly easy to solve, except one (called the peg game), that was not explained clearly. Anyone who solve at least one problem, would be qualified for the first round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This competition could attract a fairly large number of young people around the world, and by that means, it can be counted as a success. Nevertheless, there were some fundamental design problems regarding the competition website itself, which is the topic of this post. These are some of the points that came into my mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First of all, the rules and regulations of the competition, and the instructions were not presented clearly. Everything was distributed, and there were no centralized approach For instance, one had to register for this round through the event page that was created for this purpose. There was a link in the event description, that  could be used to register. when the event started, additional link were added to the same place which was pointing people to the qualification problem page. I was expecting to see the instructions in the new page and after reading all, I could not find out how I should submit my answers. Thus, I decided to open one problem and after reading that I thought maybe I have to download the input to get the instructions !!! After doing that, I opened the file and could just see some numbers in there. So, I decided to go back to the problem page and all of a sudden I saw the time is counting down. Then I went back to the event page and found out that instructions were added to the event description, under the registration link, and it was also could not be seen unless you click on *&amp;#8220;see more&amp;#8221; *to view the instructions. In addition, news and updates were being posted on another page (Hacker Cup page), and in the last day it seems they took off the  6 minute limit, but I again I failed to get updated, as I did not know such things were going on in a separate page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The second issue was related to 6 minute limit for submitting the answers. I agree that there should be some mechanisms that make sure solutions are in the range that designers expect, but in this case it was a very bad idea to control the solutions by a timer. What designers might have thought is that if the code is well-written enough, even if program fails once or twice, well, there should be still enough time for people to run their code and copy-paste the answer. At first glance it seems fair, but they failed to take other parameters into consideration. If people were using same computers with same internet connection, and of course same browsers (it seems chrome had some problems with downloading the input file), and under same circumstances it could be considered as fair. What if someone do not have access to broadband or the connection drops frequently !? Or someone has access to a very powerful computer system which despite any bad coding styles could deliver the answer in less than the amount of time provided ?! My own problem was the &amp;#8220;Peg&amp;#8217;s game&amp;#8221; input, it was big for Putty to handle, so it freeze twice (I was coding on another machine through SSH). Then I had to  start the FTP service, upload the file via FTP, and voila 6 minutes passed !&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The other problem was related to the explanation of the &amp;#8220;Peg&amp;#8217;s game&amp;#8221;. I think it was the most awful description I&amp;#8217;ve ever read in my life. The problem was a piece of cake when one fully understands it. But I think the main challenge here was understanding it. It took me a while to decrypt what was the real purpose of the question and how everything is connected together. I thought maybe it&amp;#8217;s me, and I did search today in order to see if others had any concerns about this problem. As I started to search, I found tons of different interpretations of the problem. So it seems that the designer failed to explain the problem clearly. I think it is related to the *Curse of Knowledge *(Refer to Made to Stick), which claims that the more you know about a subject the less you could know how it feels not knowing about that subject. It probably happened to you too, trying to explain something which seems obvious to you but others cannot understand a thing you are saying.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The last issue is the name of the competition does not match the content of it. They call it a hacker cup, though there were nothing to hack here, just simple programming questions. I took part in &lt;a title=&#34;HackU&#34; href=&#34;http://developer.yahoo.com/hacku/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Yahoo! HackU&lt;/a&gt; last year in University of Waterloo, and it was closer to a hacking competition than this competition. HackU is about using various tools to come up with a neat idea that blow judge&amp;#8217;s mind. I hope next rounds get closer to hacking idea than solving problems. Current situation seems more like Facebook is saying: &amp;#8220;Interviewing this amount of programmers is gonna take a lot of time, we prefer to make a competition online to select our programmers among them. And it&amp;#8217;s a better way cause people have to prove themselves&amp;#8221;. Which is absolutely fine, ( I think all the competitions are all about this), but the only hacking was to hack designers&amp;#8217; mind and the website to get the instructions and understand the problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, it is a very good move from Facebook to gather all this people to compete against each other and express their opinions. I Specially liked the way people could express their opinions on the event wall, there were lots of interesting posts, and most of them could be counted as a feedback ( Which was effective at least for taking off the time limit). I hope in the next round, geeks do not design the website, and get help from more experienced people in this area to take all the basic requirements into considerations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_facebook&#39; st\_title=&#39;Some Notes on Facebook Hacker Cup Qualification Round&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2011/01/11/some-notes-on-facebook-hacker-cup-qualification-round/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span st\_via=&#39;saman\_b&#39; class=&#39;st\_twitter&#39; st\_title=&#39;Some Notes on Facebook Hacker Cup Qualification Round&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2011/01/11/some-notes-on-facebook-hacker-cup-qualification-round/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_email&#39; st\_title=&#39;Some Notes on Facebook Hacker Cup Qualification Round&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2011/01/11/some-notes-on-facebook-hacker-cup-qualification-round/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_sharethis&#39; st\_title=&#39;Some Notes on Facebook Hacker Cup Qualification Round&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2011/01/11/some-notes-on-facebook-hacker-cup-qualification-round/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_fblike&#39; st\_title=&#39;Some Notes on Facebook Hacker Cup Qualification Round&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2011/01/11/some-notes-on-facebook-hacker-cup-qualification-round/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_plusone&#39; st\_title=&#39;Some Notes on Facebook Hacker Cup Qualification Round&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2011/01/11/some-notes-on-facebook-hacker-cup-qualification-round/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_pinterest&#39; st\_title=&#39;Some Notes on Facebook Hacker Cup Qualification Round&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2011/01/11/some-notes-on-facebook-hacker-cup-qualification-round/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Power of Free</title>
      <link>http://samanbarghi.com/2010/07/13/the-power-of-free</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://samanbarghi.com/2010/07/13/the-power-of-free</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am no coffee drinker, I prefer green tea and herbal tea over coffee. I rarely break this habit, only if I am too sleepy or really crave coffee. But once I was in a gathering in Davis Center (at University of Waterloo) and they were offering free coffee and donuts. All of a sudden I found myself socializing and drinking coffee without having any good reason for breaking my habit, I could not justify my behavior at the time. After giving some thoughts to the matter, I came up with two reasons to justify this behavior; either that was the effect of the coffee being free, or the socializing effect; I wanted to be like others. Now there are two questions to be asked:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first question is: is all the stuff that are being offered to you for free, are actually free? What are the hidden costs of free stuff for you? How much are you paying (mentally and physically) to get something that worth nothing (money wise)? Dan Ariely describe and [experiment ][1] that he runs about free ice cream in his blog. He claims that free stuff are not actually free, cause for example you are investing your time in the line to get an ice cream that worth $1.45. But is that the only price you are paying? What about an overweight person who is on a diet and happened to pass by Ben &amp;amp; Jerry, and decides to get one ice-cream cause it&amp;#8217;s free? (Yeah will power is effective here, but sometimes FREE is more tempting than anything else)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other situations rather than free ice-cream, such as free shampoos given away, shavers, &amp;#8230;. In all these cases they are changing your mentality towards their company. Now your unconscious might tend to make you believe that this company is generous and you might want to do them a favor back in the future and buy their products later, and become a loyal costumer. Most of the companies are smarter and try to make you dependent on their products, think about all the blades you bought from a certain company because you got the razor for free! These are all hidden costs of free stuff which are not obvious in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second question to be asked is: how much are you willing to sacrifice to be part of a group? How many values are you going to destroy to be mentally close to the ones who are around you? Again this is related to will power, to hold on to your values and what you believe-in, even when others around you are making you feel bad about it. We are all seeking for approval from other people, that&amp;#8217;s why we try to look like others. Nevertheless, what is the life you are seeing in front of you? The one you take control of it or the one others control for you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_facebook&#39; st\_title=&#39;The Power of Free&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/07/13/the-power-of-free/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span st\_via=&#39;saman\_b&#39; class=&#39;st\_twitter&#39; st\_title=&#39;The Power of Free&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/07/13/the-power-of-free/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_email&#39; st\_title=&#39;The Power of Free&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/07/13/the-power-of-free/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_sharethis&#39; st\_title=&#39;The Power of Free&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/07/13/the-power-of-free/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_fblike&#39; st\_title=&#39;The Power of Free&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/07/13/the-power-of-free/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_plusone&#39; st\_title=&#39;The Power of Free&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/07/13/the-power-of-free/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_pinterest&#39; st\_title=&#39;The Power of Free&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/07/13/the-power-of-free/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]: &lt;a href=&#34;http://danariely.com/2008/02/29/free-2/&#34;&gt;http://danariely.com/2008/02/29/free-2/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rationality</title>
      <link>http://samanbarghi.com/2010/04/12/rationality</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://samanbarghi.com/2010/04/12/rationality</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are moments in life when you have to make a big decision, however, your emotions and ego block your mind. You cannot think clearly, and you see everything the way you want them to be, but the reality is on the exact opposite side. If you just rely on yourself and float in your thoughts, you are gonna drown at the very bottom of these thoughts. There is no way out of your doubts and uncertainty, it either makes you go crazy or  never let you get in touch with reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are trapped in a box created by you, and you cannot see out of the box, all you need is to break the wall and see outside of the box. But not everybody is strong enough to overcome their fears of what they are about to see and embrace the reality. These are the exact moments that friends were created for, you need someone that sees outside the box. If you consult the situation with someone else, someone you trust, you can see through his eyes and step by step see the light of reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very familiar example is a broken relationship. I have seen many people get emotional when the other person leaves them or cheat on them after they have been in a relationship for a while. They do not want to believe that either the other side does not want them, or they cannot trust the other side anymore. They see through the eyes of their memories and all the good moments they had together. The first thing they do is not letting the other side go, as the low self-confidence created by the rejection makes them hold on to that person harder. It gets harder and harder for them to believe the other side is cheated on them or does not want them, what they want to believe is that everything is back to normal and they can fix things. They tend to believe every lies that the other side is telling them, they can be easily played. They can survive if a friend come to the scene and open their eyes to their reality, it feels awful but they have to do what has to be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main question here is how to detect these moments ? How to stay in touch with reality all the time and keep emotions away? What should you do after you detected you trapped in a box? how can you see outside of the box with your own power and without getting any help from someone else? What will be the possible practice to strengthen this ability?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EDIT:&lt;/strong&gt; Also, check the following: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/frontal-cortex/2012/06/daniel-kahneman-bias-studies.html&#34;&gt;http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/frontal-cortex/2012/06/daniel-kahneman-bias-studies.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_facebook&#39; st\_title=&#39;Rationality&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/04/12/rationality/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span st\_via=&#39;saman\_b&#39; class=&#39;st\_twitter&#39; st\_title=&#39;Rationality&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/04/12/rationality/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_email&#39; st\_title=&#39;Rationality&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/04/12/rationality/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_sharethis&#39; st\_title=&#39;Rationality&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/04/12/rationality/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_fblike&#39; st\_title=&#39;Rationality&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/04/12/rationality/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_plusone&#39; st\_title=&#39;Rationality&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/04/12/rationality/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_pinterest&#39; st\_title=&#39;Rationality&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/04/12/rationality/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>See ID</title>
      <link>http://samanbarghi.com/2010/04/12/see-id</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://samanbarghi.com/2010/04/12/see-id</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I used to be asked to show my ID every time  I was paying by my credit card, and yes you are right, I did not sign the back of my credit card (That is how it works in Canada, they are taking it to the next level for entering a PIN number though). Today I was asked to show my ID again, but I noticed  no one has asked me to show my ID for last two months. Surprisingly, I could successfully stop ID checks without signing the back of my credit card. You are probably confused, but it is not that complicated. Instead of signing the back, I simply wrote &amp;#8220;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;See ID&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;#8221; on the signature area. It was supposed to make cashiers to ask more about my ID, but to my surprise it worked the other way !&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does anyone has a rational explanation for the fake trust created by writing such a sentence? The first question I asked myself was  if the sentence created some sort of trust, or it is just because people do not like to do what they are told to do. What makes people more trustful when you directly tell them what you expect them to do!? I will start to do some research to find a proper answer to my question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_facebook&#39; st\_title=&#39;See ID&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/04/12/see-id/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span st\_via=&#39;saman\_b&#39; class=&#39;st\_twitter&#39; st\_title=&#39;See ID&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/04/12/see-id/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_email&#39; st\_title=&#39;See ID&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/04/12/see-id/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_sharethis&#39; st\_title=&#39;See ID&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/04/12/see-id/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_fblike&#39; st\_title=&#39;See ID&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/04/12/see-id/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_plusone&#39; st\_title=&#39;See ID&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/04/12/see-id/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_pinterest&#39; st\_title=&#39;See ID&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/04/12/see-id/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The power of options</title>
      <link>http://samanbarghi.com/2010/03/16/the-power-of-options</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://samanbarghi.com/2010/03/16/the-power-of-options</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The library of Davis Center at University of Waterloo is a fairly popular place for students to spend their time studying. There is this quiet section, with separate study space for each student equipped with florescent lighting, where seems to be the most popular place in the library. Based on the time of day, if exams time is close or not, if it is a weekend or not, and some other parameters, two possible scenarios might happen; the place is either packed or is half empty. Now, the interesting part is how students behave while looking for a place in this section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets consider the first scenario when the study area is packed;  in this case all desks are occupied and if you get lucky and be fast, you might be able to find an empty spot. So in this case you have to walk fast, focus on what you are looking for, and as soon as finding an empty spot,  you sit down without a second thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, there are more available seats on the second scenario as you walk in to the study area. Considering the first case, you should be happy with the first available spot. This time students show a totally different behavior (including me). Now that they have more options, they do not simply sit on the first available spot they find unlike the former situation. Students tend to have &lt;strong&gt;preferences&lt;/strong&gt;, they take their time to walk around and find their **preferred **spot, although the seats are exactly the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened? Students developed preferences when they had more options, and were fully satisfied with their choice when there were no options available. After observing this behavior, I recalled the &lt;a title=&#34;Barry Schartws on the Paradox of Choice&#34; href=&#34;http://www.ted.com/talks/barry_schwartz_on_the_paradox_of_choice.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Barry Schwartz TED talk on the &amp;#8220;Paradox of Choice&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;. In this talk he notes the availability of more choices made us more paralyzed and dissatisfied rather than free and satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can observe such a scenario in your everyday life; in relationships for example,  you are always looking for a better match, if you think there is someone better for you out there, you will be unhappy about your relationship.  As another example, when I started my PhD, I had the option to get a job instead, so sometimes I feel finding a job could have been a better choice at that time, and thinking about the possible benefits of a job making me dissatisfied. If I only had the PhD option I could have been happier as I knew that was the only choice I had.  As a graduate student in Canada, during the winter I do more studying than summer, why? Good weather during the summer is the answer, I have the option to go out and enjoy the weather instead of sitting in my office without any windows (The funny thing about the Computer Science department at University of Waterloo is that it made out of glass but none of the offices have windows !!! Yet as you can see, this is another example of being dissatisfied as I am aware of the option of having an office with windows). Even reading a book such as David Allen&amp;#8217;s  &lt;a title=&#34;Getting Things Done&#34; href=&#34;http://www.amazon.ca/Getting-Things-Done-David-Allen/dp/0142000280/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;#8220;Getting Things Done (GTD)&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;,  make you spend a week or two to find a good way of implementing it. The reason is that there are too many options for starting such a system.  I, myself ended up using a &lt;a title=&#34;Moleskine&#34; href=&#34;http://www.moleskine.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;moleskine&lt;/a&gt; and a pen at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This simple aspect of people&amp;#8217;s behavior can be very powerful for marketing ideas. Dan Areily in &lt;a title=&#34;Predictably Irrational&#34; href=&#34;http://www.predictablyirrational.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;#8220;Predictably Irrational&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt; give an example on the first bread maker. When bread makers were first introduced they were not selling good, as people could not find a reason to buy one. But when the company introduced the second bread maker which was more expensive than the first one, people started to buy the first bread maker and sales took off. People started to have something to compare the first bread maker with, and since it was priced more reasonably they found the urge to buy it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One another obvious example, which you might have experienced, is the store sales and discounts. Not all but some people tend to buy everything that they find on sale, even if they do not need it. I have a friend who is addicted to shopping, it does not matter what it is as long as it is on sale, it is good to buy, Why? It is just about the good and victorious feeling that he has after finding a deal, and he can talk about it for hours. There is no doubt that you have experienced the same feeling, think of the moments you were talking about a good deal you found on your favorite gadget (or dress).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look it from another angle, these deals can make you dissatisfied as well. For instance, I was trying to buy a laptop backpack and found hundreds of them online, it took me almost two weeks to make a decision and choose one. However, at the end if you hear someone talking about a deal on backpack laptops or you happen to go to a store with a better and cheaper backpack you will be dissatisfied immediately. There is this documentary about &lt;a title=&#34;How to make better decisions&#34; href=&#34;http://topdocumentaryfilms.com/how-to-make-better-decisions/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;how to make better decisions&lt;/a&gt; from BBC, the experiments in this documentary are surprisingly unbelievable. There is an experiment, in which two photos from different persons are shown to the participants. They choose one of them that they like more than the other, with a simple trick the photo they did not like is given to them instead of the one they ed more. Now, the participants are asked :why they like that person? (of course, without knowing that this person is not the one they chose). They start explaining the reasons although they did not have any interest in that person. This experiment shows how people can simply change their mind and be satisfied with the new situation, if the options are removed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tim Harford in his book, &lt;a title=&#34;The logic of Life&#34; href=&#34;http://timharford.com/logicoflife/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;#8220;The logic of Life&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;, gives another example about this issue. He provides an experiment over speed dating, where random people are brought to a room and they have limited time to talk to each other, and at the end,  each person pick a match based on their standards.  Tim notes that girls are more attracted to tall guys and guys are more attracted to thin girls. Imagine that, in a speed dating night there are 20 guys and 20 girls. Tim says that if there is a short guy among the guys and other guys are mostly tall, the short guy most probably will not get a date. However, if all 20 guys are short in the session, girls lower their expectations, compromise with the new situation and the chance of each short guy of being picked is higher. The story is the same for fat girls.  As you can see, adding or removing choices will make people act differently, although the short guy is still the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, it seems that &lt;strong&gt;choice&lt;/strong&gt; is a very powerful parameter that shapes the decisions we make. Providing more choices, or removing them can be easily used by businesses, governments and advertisers to control our life without us even knowing it.  As Barry Schwartz states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;one should lower his expectations to be more happy&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_facebook&#39; st\_title=&#39;The power of options&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/03/16/the-power-of-options/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span st\_via=&#39;saman\_b&#39; class=&#39;st\_twitter&#39; st\_title=&#39;The power of options&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/03/16/the-power-of-options/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_email&#39; st\_title=&#39;The power of options&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/03/16/the-power-of-options/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_sharethis&#39; st\_title=&#39;The power of options&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/03/16/the-power-of-options/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_fblike&#39; st\_title=&#39;The power of options&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/03/16/the-power-of-options/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_plusone&#39; st\_title=&#39;The power of options&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/03/16/the-power-of-options/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#39;st\_pinterest&#39; st\_title=&#39;The power of options&#39; st_url=&#39;http://www.samanbarghi.com/2010/03/16/the-power-of-options/&#39;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>