<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Saman Barghi</title>
    <link>http://samanbarghi.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Saman Barghi</description>
    <image>
      <url>http://samanbarghi.com/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</url>
      <link>http://samanbarghi.com/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2016 10:40:49 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://samanbarghi.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Generate C interface from C&#43;&#43; source code using Clang libtooling</title>
      <link>http://samanbarghi.com/post/using-clang-libtooling-to-generate-c-interface-from-c&#43;&#43;-source-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2016 10:40:49 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://samanbarghi.com/post/using-clang-libtooling-to-generate-c-interface-from-c&#43;&#43;-source-code/</guid>
      <description>Using Clang libtooling for LLVM to generate C interface from C&#43;&#43; source code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>http://samanbarghi.com/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2016 00:27:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://samanbarghi.com/projects/</guid>
      <description>My projects</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://samanbarghi.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2015 02:09:03 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://samanbarghi.com/about/</guid>
      <description>About Saman Barghi</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to wrap a system call (libc function) in Linux</title>
      <link>http://samanbarghi.com/post/2014-09-05-how-to-wrap-a-system-call-libc-function-in-linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://samanbarghi.com/post/2014-09-05-how-to-wrap-a-system-call-libc-function-in-linux/</guid>
      <description>For one of my research projects I had to wrap linux system calls and redirect them to another thread. In Linux system calls are not invoked directly, but rather via wrapper functions in glibc[man 2 syscalls]. The glibc wrapper is only copying arguments and unique system call number to the registers where the kernel expects them, then trapping to kernel mode and setting the errno if the system call returns an error number [man 2 intro].</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>National Geographic Photo of the day Downloader for Linux</title>
      <link>http://samanbarghi.com/2012/08/29/national-geographic-photo-of-the-day-downloader-for-linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://samanbarghi.com/2012/08/29/national-geographic-photo-of-the-day-downloader-for-linux/</guid>
      <description>National Geographic&amp;#39;s Photo Of the Day I am a fan of National Geographic photos on their site, and I also get bored of by my desktop background after a while. So I decided to create a script to download National Geographic photo of the day, and using it as my desktop background. I am using it over Gnome3 (I am using Fedora as I think it’s more stable than Ubuntu, and I like Gnome3 way better than Unity), but if you are a Unity user it should work for you as well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Might My Resume look Like If I Were a Computer !?</title>
      <link>http://samanbarghi.com/2012/05/21/what-might-my-resume-look-like-if-i-were-a-computer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://samanbarghi.com/2012/05/21/what-might-my-resume-look-like-if-i-were-a-computer/</guid>
      <description>The other day I was about to update my resume, and this crazy question came to my mind: What might my resume look like if I were a computer ?
And This is the result. (Best viewed in Chrome and Firefox).
Well, I am aware that I would not wake up one morning finding out I turned into a computer. Also, I am not sure if one day I turn into a computer, I would look for a job.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mercurial on Bluehost</title>
      <link>http://samanbarghi.com/2011/08/26/mercurial-on-bluehost/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://samanbarghi.com/2011/08/26/mercurial-on-bluehost/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SSH to VirtualBox 3 FreeBsd Guests</title>
      <link>http://samanbarghi.com/2011/02/04/ssh-to-virtualbox-3-freebsd-guests/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://samanbarghi.com/2011/02/04/ssh-to-virtualbox-3-freebsd-guests/</guid>
      <description>This post is based on “Howto: SSH into VirtualBox 3 Linux Guests” by Stuart Colville, which I have updated to work for FreeBSD Guests: In older versions of VirtualBox one had to use a bridge interface to make this work. However, in newer versions; a virtual interface can be added to the Host by default, which make it way easier to access the guest machine through the host.
Usually, you have a primary network interface which uses NAT adapter, that one is needed for connecting to the Internet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some Notes on Facebook Hacker Cup Qualification Round</title>
      <link>http://samanbarghi.com/2011/01/11/some-notes-on-facebook-hacker-cup-qualification-round/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://samanbarghi.com/2011/01/11/some-notes-on-facebook-hacker-cup-qualification-round/</guid>
      <description>Monday, January 10 was the last day to submit your answers to get qualified for Facebook Hacker Cup. It started from January 7, and lasted for 3 days. There were three problems presented on the competition website, to be solved by participants. Problems were provided with sample input and output, and there were no time limits to browse through the problems and to develop your code. To answer each problem, competitors had to download an input and submit their output, yet they only had 6 minutes, after they downloaded the input, to submit their answers through the form provided.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Power of Free</title>
      <link>http://samanbarghi.com/2010/07/13/the-power-of-free/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://samanbarghi.com/2010/07/13/the-power-of-free/</guid>
      <description>I am no coffee drinker, I prefer green tea and herbal tea over coffee. I rarely break this habit, only if I am too sleepy or really crave coffee. But once I was in a gathering in Davis Center (at University of Waterloo) and they were offering free coffee and donuts. All of a sudden I found myself socializing and drinking coffee without having any good reason for breaking my habit, I could not justify my behavior at the time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rationality</title>
      <link>http://samanbarghi.com/2010/04/12/rationality/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://samanbarghi.com/2010/04/12/rationality/</guid>
      <description>There are moments in life when you have to make a big decision, however, your emotions and ego block your mind. You cannot think clearly, and you see everything the way you want them to be, but the reality is on the exact opposite side. If you just rely on yourself and float in your thoughts, you are gonna drown at the very bottom of these thoughts. There is no way out of your doubts and uncertainty, it either makes you go crazy or never let you get in touch with reality.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>See ID</title>
      <link>http://samanbarghi.com/2010/04/12/see-id/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://samanbarghi.com/2010/04/12/see-id/</guid>
      <description>I used to be asked to show my ID every time I was paying by my credit card, and yes you are right, I did not sign the back of my credit card (That is how it works in Canada, they are taking it to the next level for entering a PIN number though). Today I was asked to show my ID again, but I noticed no one has asked me to show my ID for last two months.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SPDY installation</title>
      <link>http://samanbarghi.com/2010/03/31/spdy-installation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://samanbarghi.com/2010/03/31/spdy-installation/</guid>
      <description>I am taking a course called “Latency in Communication Systems” taught by Martin Karsten in University of Waterloo. We talked about different aspects of latency in communication systems, there were some lectures from industry (Sandvine, TD Securites, RIM, and SUN/Oracle) about what were the different problems they were facing during their system implementation. I had also presented two papers on profiling and router performance during the course. My course project is the reason I am writing this post, I have to install and evaluate SPDY.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The power of options</title>
      <link>http://samanbarghi.com/2010/03/16/the-power-of-options/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://samanbarghi.com/2010/03/16/the-power-of-options/</guid>
      <description>The library of Davis Center at University of Waterloo is a fairly popular place for students to spend their time studying. There is this quiet section, with separate study space for each student equipped with florescent lighting, where seems to be the most popular place in the library. Based on the time of day, if exams time is close or not, if it is a weekend or not, and some other parameters, two possible scenarios might happen; the place is either packed or is half empty.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
